<?xml version='1.0' encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>

<chapter id="jpa-course-description">
    <title>Course Description</title>

    <section id="jpa-meeting">
        <title>Meeting Times/Location</title>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem><para>Wednesdays, 4:00-6:00pm</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>via Webex</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="jpa-description">
        <title>Description</title>
        <para>
        This course focuses on the development of a Java application data tier using the Java Persistence API (JPA).
        The course will introduce:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem><para>the role of the data tier</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>the basics of object/relational mapping using the JPA API</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>different means of querying (JPA-QL, Native, and Criteria)</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>optimization and tuning techniques</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>deploying the JPA-based data tier server-side</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
        The course is taught in the context of an overall JavaEE development. Eclipse and Maven are 
        used to demonstrate techniques for building and testing data tier components. Weekly exercises are
        provided to give each student plenty of chances for hands-on work. 
        </para> 
    </section>

    <section id="jpa-objective">
        <title>Course Objectives</title>
        <para>
            This course will provide the student with the ability to design and implement a data tier 
            using JPA and be able to identify pitfalls and implement optimized solutions. 
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="jpa-student-background">
        <title>Student Background</title>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem><para>Java development skills are required to actively complete the exercises.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="jpa-student-commitment">
        <title>Student Commitment</title>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem><para>Students should be prepared to spend between 2-4 hours a week outside of class.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="jpa-texts">
        <title>Course Text(s)</title>
        <section id="jpa-texts-recommended">
            <title>Recommended Text(s)</title>
            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
	            <listitem><para>
	            <emphasis>"Pro JPA 2, 2nd Edition"</emphasis>, 
	            Mike Keith and Merrick Schincariol, 2013, O'Reilly, ISBN-10: 1430249269; ISBN-13: 978-1430249269 
	            </para>
	            </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
        
    <section id="jpa-required-software">
        <title>Required Software</title>
        <para>
            This course will make heavy use of development tools
            (Git, Maven 3, JUnit, Log4j, and Eclipse), a database 
            (H2 Database Engine), and persistence provider
            (Hibernate). An application server (JBoss EAP 6/AS 7) will be part 
            of the targeted deployment environment, but not central to the 
            course concepts.  Students are strongly encouraged to establish a local
            development environment. Detailed instructions for setup are
            part of the first exercise (Development Environment Setup).
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="jpa-references">
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            The core of the JPA 2.1 content is covered in the primary text for 
            the course (and competing texts as well as online). Associated 
            topics (database schema, SQL, and tools) are not 
            covered in the course text, but documentation will be provided 
            through course slides, examples, and tutorials.        
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="jpa-grading">
        <title>Grading</title>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem><para>Attendance in five out of the six classes is required for credit</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Make-up work is available and can be completed to receive credit for class(es) missed</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    

    <section id="jpa-instructor-availability">
        <title>Instructor Availability</title>
        <para>
            I am available in the AM, before/after class, and evenings. I can conduct
            one-on-one webex sessions on class day and evenings. I do not have access
            to the Internet or SRA-net during the normal work day. I will check the 
            e-mail and the class discussion group mornings, end-of-day, and evenings.
        </para>
        <para>
            Note: I picked the end-of-day time for class to not have class smack in the 
            middle of the day and allow you time to get to a useful location (or provide
            you an alternative activity to driving in rush-hour traffic).
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
  
