<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Enterprise Java (605.784) Course Description</title>
    <author email="jcstaff@apl.jhu.edu">Jim Stafford</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <h4>Enterprise Java (605.784.31) Fall 2006</h4>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>Wednesdays, 4:30-7:10pm</li>
        <li>APL, K1</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h5>Course Description</h5>
          <p>
            This course focuses on the Java Platform, Enterprise Edition
            (Java EE) for the development of multi-tier applications.            
          </p>
          <p>
          The course is divided up into three main areas; data access, 
            n-tier applications, and asynchronous applications.            
          </p>
          <ul>
            <li>Data Access - this will cover data access patterns,
            Java Database Connectivity (JDBC), and the EJB3 Java 
            Persistence API.
            </li>
            <li>N-Tier Applications - will cover data access integration 
            into Web applications, Remote Method Invocation (RMI), 
            Session Beans, Java Naming and 
            Directory Interface (JNDI), Java Transaction API (JTA),
            Java EE Security, and Enterprise Archives (EARs)
            </li>
            <li>Asynchronous Applications - will cover the Java Message
            Service (JMS), Message Driven Beans (MDBs), and Timers
            </li>
          </ul>              
          <p>
          Using modern development tools, commercial persistence 
          providers, and application servers, students will design and 
          implement several significant programming projects using the
          above mentioned technologies and deploy them to a Java EE 
          environment that they will manage.            
          </p>

    <h5>Student Background</h5>
    <ul>
      <li>Prerequisite: 605.481 Distributed Development on the 
          World Wide Web or equivalent.
      </li>
      <li>Strong Java programming skills are assumed.</li>
    </ul>

    <h5>Student Commitment</h5>
    <ul>
      <li>Students should be prepared to spend between 10-16 
          hours a week outside of class. 
      </li>
    </ul>

    <h5>Required Course Texts</h5>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/entjbeans5/cover.html">
      Enterprise Java Beans 3.0, 5th Edition</a>;
        <a href="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;safe=off&amp;q=ISBN%20059600978X&amp;btnG=Search&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=wf">
          ISBN 059600978X
        </a>; Bill Burke, Sacha Labourey, and Richard Monson-Haefel;
        O'Reilly, 2006 
      </li>
    </ul>    

    <h5>Recommended Course Texts</h5>
    <ul>
      <li>A Servlet/JSP Text
        <ul>
          <li>Core Servlets and JavaServer Pages (JSP), 
          2nd Edition, Marty Hall, 2003, 
          Prentice Hall PTR; 
          ISBN 0130092290</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>        

    <h5>Required Software</h5>
    <p>
      This course will make heavy use of development tools (Subversion
      client, Maven 2, JUnit, Log4j, and Eclipse),
      databases (Hypersonic; comes with JBoss), persistence providers
      (Hibernate; comes with JBoss), and application servers (JBoss).
      Students are strongly encouraged to establish a local development
      environment. Detailed instructions for setup are part of the first
      exercise (<a href="./exercises/ex0.html">Development Environment 
      Setup</a>). 
    </p>
    
    <h5>References</h5>
    <p>
      Much of the material in this course is either new or changing. 
      Some of the referenced texts or the material they cover can 
      be obtained on-line as well as through book stores. The form in 
      which you access this material is up to you. A list of online 
      <a href="./links.html">references</a> can be found on this site.
      Each lecture will supply a list of references for that technical 
      area.
    </p>
    <h5>Grading</h5>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          100 &gt;= A &gt;= 90 &gt; B &gt;= 80 &gt; C &gt;= 70 &gt; F;
        </li>
        <li>
          Students will be graded on three projects and quizzes.
          Projects will be done individually and graded 100 though 0.
          A quiz, based on sample questions supplied with the project 
          assignment, will be held in the class immediately after a project
          is due. Quizzes are <b>closed</b> to notes/text. Students 
          not attending a quiz will be required to take a make-up quiz
          through the college office.      
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Assessment</th>
        <th>% of Semester Grade</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Project 1</td>
        <td>30%</td>
      </tr>      
      <tr>
        <td>Quiz 1</td>
        <td>10%</td>
      </tr>      
      <tr>
        <td>Project 2</td>
        <td>30%</td>
      </tr>      
      <tr>
        <td>Quiz 2</td>
        <td>10%</td>
      </tr>      
      <tr>
        <td>Project 3</td>
        <td>15%</td>
      </tr>      
      <tr>
        <td>Quiz 3</td>
        <td>5%</td>
      </tr>      
    </table>      
    </p>
    
    <h5>Grading Policy</h5>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <b>Late projects will be deducted 10pts/week late, starting 
          after the due date/time, with one exception.</b> 
          A student may submit a <b>single</b> 
          project up to 4 days late without receiving approval and still 
          receive complete credit. Students taking advantage of the 
          free first pass should still submit an e-mail to the graders
          notifying them of their intent.
        </li>
        <li>
          Projects must be submitted via e-mail to the graders with source 
          code in one zip file with a README. Pre-build artifacts must also 
          be included in the submission. All source code must be written to 
          portably compile in the grader's environment using Maven 2 or Ant.
        </li>
        <li>
          Class attendance is <b>strongly</b> recommended, but not
          mandatory. The student is responsible for obtaining any written or
          oral information covered during their absence.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    
    <h5>Academic Integrity</h5>
    <p>
      <ul>
          <li>
          Collaboration of ideas and approaches are strongly encouraged.
          You may use partial solutions provided by others as a part of 
          your project submission. However, the bulk usage of another 
          students implementation or project will result in a 0 for the 
          project. There is a difference between sharing ideas/code snippets
          and turning in someone else's work as your own. When in doubt,
          document your sources.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    
    <h5>Instructor Availability</h5>
    <p>
        I am available mostly through 
        <a href="mailto:jcstaff@apl.jhu.edu">e-mail</a> and the 
        <a href="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/ejava_class">newsgroup</a> 
        to go through
        all issues in detail. Use the class newsgroup for all technical issues.
        Use my e-mail for issues of more of a personal nature.
        I have some availability before class or during
        breaks. Students needing further assistance are also welcome to visit 
        <a href="http://www.raba.com">my office in Columbia</a> when necessary.
    </p>
  </body>
</document>

